Guide to the Murray Frank papers, 1919-1971 MS2073
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Murray Frank papers
1919-1971
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Frank, Murray
MS2073
0.5 Linear Feet
This collection consists of manuscript and lecture notes, and one speech and is dated from 1919-1971. Murray Frank had a varied career that included writing and teaching. Most of his work related to Jewish issues.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Joan Lippman, Executive Administrator of the Jewish Historical Society of Maryland, Inc. in 1983.
Historical or Biographical Note
Murray Frank (1908-1977), a 1936 graduate of The George Washington University, had a varied career. He worked as an administrative assistant on Capitol Hill, an economic analyst, a journalist concentrating on Jewish issues for Jewish publications, a broadcaster, and an author and teacher. He was active in the Jewish community in Washington and on a national level. From 1963 until the mid 1970s, Frank was an administrative assistant to U.S. Representative William L. St. Onge. Prior to that he was an administrative assistant to U.S. Representative Abraham J. Multer (1949-51) and U.S. Representative Victor I. Anfuso (1955-65).
Other service to the U.S. Government included a stint as an economic analyst at the Department of Commerce (1941-52) followed by a position in the United States Foreign Economic Administration from 1942-45. From 1949-51 he was an advisor on Jewish affairs to U.S. Representative Sol Bloom. Many Jewish publications had Murray Frank as a contributing journalist. These publications included "The Day Jewish Journal," "Jewish Morning Journal," "Jewish Chronicle," "Yiddishe Zeiting" (Buenos Aires), "Davar" (Israel), "American Zionist," and the "National Jewish Post."
Frank was the director and announcer for "The Voice of Israel" a weekly radio program on WDON and WASH-FM. in Washington, D.C. from 1958-61.
As an author, Frank produced the following volumes: "Fisheries of Latin America," "The War Refuge Board," and "This is B'nai B'rith, Book of Facts." He coauthored "Industrialization of Latin America" and was the editor and information director of "B'nai B'rith News" from 1945-47.
Frank's teaching career began in the District of Columbia public schools. He taught in the District from 1937-41. He later taught Jewish history at the College of Jewish Studies in Washington, D.C. (1949-51) and the Temple Sinai adult education program where his offering included post-biblical Jewish literature.
Very active in the community in Washington, Frank was president of Farband LZOA from 1961-68, vice-president of Washington Community for Shaare Zedek Hospital in Jerusalem, vice-chair of the government division United Jewish Appeal, a representative to the American Jewish Conference, 1945-46, a memer of the Board of Directors of the Jewish Community Center from 1941-44, the Jewish Social Service Agency, 1944-46, and the Hebrew Academy of Washington, 1950-54. He was also a member of the J.L. Peretz American Academy of Political Science, the Congressional Press Gallery, the White House News Correspondence Association, and the State Department Correspondence Association.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of manuscript and lecture notes, and one speech. The collection consists entirely of manuscripts and lecture notes. The language of the material is English for the most part, some documents are in cursive Yiddish. This information is noted in the Folder Content Listing. The following arbitrary divisions were imposed on the material because no original order was apparent: Israel, Judaism, Library of Congress, Literature., United States, Zionism, miscellaneous lecture notes, Press Releases.
Collection note
From original finding aid: secondary sources were deaccessioned. clipping files were also deaccessioned because no annotations were involved.
Washington (D.C.); Judaism; Literature; Zionism; United States; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Frank, Murray
- Israel: Eliahu Epstein Israel's First Representative in Washington (Box 1, Folder 1 item 1)
  General note
  [From original finding aid]: (7 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Israel Foreign Policy in Israel: The Story of Moshe Sharett (Box 1, Folder 1 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (19 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Israel's Foreign Minister The Story of Moshe Sharett (Box 1, Folder 1 item 3)
- Israel: Moshe Sharett, Boss of Israel's Foreign Affairs (Box 1, Folder 1 item 4)
  [From original finding aid]: (17 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Israel's Front Man---Israel's Shertok (Box 1, Folder 1 item 5)
  [From original finding aid]: (11 typewritten pages, no bibliography, revised in pencil)
- America and Israel: speech (Box 1, Folder 2)
  [From original finding aid]: [1954] annotated
- Judaism: Great Jewish Books, Lecture XII, Hassidism (Box 1, Folder 3 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (7 handwritten pages)
- Judaism: Hasidism in Eastern Europe, Lecture I, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (12 handwritten pages, given Arlington-Fairfax Jewish Congregation)
- The Jewish Cultural Heritage in the Library of Congress (Box 1, Folder 4 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (4 page typewritten manuscript, no bibliography)
- The Library of Congress and the Tercentenary Congress (Box 1, Folder 4 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: 4 page typewritten manuscript, no bibliography)
- Judaica in the Library of Congress (Box 1, Folder 4 item 3)
  [From original finding aid]: (6 page typewritten manuscript, no bibliography)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture 1, Post-biblical Literature and Saddiah Gaon (Box 1, Folder 5 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (8 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture II, Rashi and His Commentaries (Box 1, Folder 5 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (5 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture III, Golden Era in Moslem Spain (I) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 3)
  [From original finding aid]: (6 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture IV, Golden Era in Moslem Spain (II) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 4)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture V, Golden Era in Moslem Spain (III) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 5)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture V1, Golden Era in Moslem Spain (IV) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 6)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture VII, Golden Era in Moslem Spain (V) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 7)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture VIII, Post-Maimonides Era (13th & 14th) (Box 1, Folder 5 item 8)
  [From original finding aid]: (7 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture IX, The Zohar and the Shulchan Aruch (Box 1, Folder 5 item 9)
- Literature: Great Jewish Hooks, Lecture X, Literature in 16th and 17th Centuries (Box 1, Folder 5 item 10)
  [From original finding aid]: (3 handwritten pages, newsclipping attachment)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture XI, Spinoza (Box 1, Folder 5 item 11)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture XIII, Mendelssohn and Haskalah Movement (Box 1, Folder 5 item 12)
- Literature: Great Jewish Hooks, Lecture XIV, Graetz and Dubnow, Jewry's Great Historians (Box 1, Folder 5 item 13)
- Literature: Great Jewish Books, Lecture XV, Founders of Modern Zionism (Box 1, Folder 5 item 14)
  [From original finding aid]: (10 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Jewish Literature (in English) Lecture I (Box 1, Folder 5 item 15)
  [From original finding aid]: (18 handwritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Solomon Ibn Gabirol - 900th Anniversary (Box 1, Folder 5 item 16)
  [From original finding aid]: (7 tablet-sized handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish)
- Literature: Yiddish Literature in Soviet Russia between the First and Second World Wars (Box 1, Folder 5 item 17)
  [From original finding aid]: (10 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish, no bibliography)
- Literature: "Sholem Aleichem and His Literary Heritage", Qhr Kodesh, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (11 typewritten tablet-size pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: "Sholem Aleichem-50 Years Later", JCC Coffee House, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (1 handwritten tablet-size pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: "Life and Times of Sholom Aleichem", MCJC, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6 item 3)
  [From original finding aid]: (1 handwritten tablet-size page)
- Literature: "Sholem Aleichem, The Man and His Works", B'nai Israel, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6 item 4)
- Literature: "Sholem Aleichem, The Mand and his Works" (Box 1, Folder 6 item 5)
  [From original finding aid]: (4 handwritten tablet-size pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Talk on Sholem Al ei chem, Medina Club-Pioneer Women, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6 item 6)
  [From original finding aid]: (6 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Literature: Shalom Aleichem and his Literary Legacy (Box 1, Folder 6 item 7)
  [From original finding aid]: (11 tablet-sized handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish, no bibliography)
- Literature: Sholem Asch-Enigma of Jewish Literature PTA, Chaim Weizmann School, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: 7 handwritten pages
- Literature: Sholem Asch, Enigma of Yiddish Literature (Box 1, Folder 7 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (12 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish)
- Literature: Yiddish Literature in Poland Between World War I-World War II, 1919-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (11 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish)
- Literature: Yiddish Literature in Poland between the World Wars (Box 1, Folder 8 item 2)
- Literature: Miscellaneous notes in cursive Yiddish: 1) The Spiritual Life of Jews and the Rise of Christianity from the Beginning of the Middle Ages. 2) Moshe Braderson (Box 1, Folder 8 item 3)
  [From original finding aid]: (3 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish)
- Literature: Modern Hebrew Literature, Lecture I (Box 1, Folder 9 item 1)
- Literature: Modern Hebrew Literature, Lecture II, The Pre-Israeli Period (Box 1, Folder 9 item 2)
- Literature: Modern Hebrew Literature, Lecture III, The Israeli Period (Box 1, Folder 9 item 3)
- Literature: I. Yiddish Literature (Box 1, Folder 9 item 4)
- Literature: II. Early Modern Period (1750 to 2nd half of 19th Century) (Box 1, Folder 9 item 5)
- Literature: III. Modern Yiddish Literature (from mid-19th Century) (Box 1, Folder 9 item 6)
- Literature: Lecture IV Modern Yiddish Literature B. Sholem Aleichem (Box 1, Folder 9 item 7)
- Literature: Lecture II Yiddish Literature in Poland (between WWI and WWII) (Box 1, Folder 9 item 8)
- Literature: Lecture III Yiddish Literature in America (WWI to present) (Box 1, Folder 9 item 9)
- Literature: Lecture IV Rise of Yiddish Literature in America (Box 1, Folder 9 item 10)
- Literature: Lecture VII Yiddish Literature From 1900 to World War I (Box 1, Folder 9 item 11)
- Literature: Lecture VIII Yiddish Literature on Eve of World War I (Box 1, Folder 9 item 12)
- Literature: Contemporary Jewish Literature Lecture I (Box 1, Folder 9 item 13)
- Literature: Speech, "How an American Jew views Israel" Jewish Community Center, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9 item 14)
  [From original finding aid]: (16 tablet-sired pages in cursive Yiddish, no bibliography)
- United States: Discrimination and the Jewish College Student (Box 1, Folder 10 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (9 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- United States: Jewish Education in the United States (Box 1, Folder 10 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (5 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Immigration: Failure of the American Refuge (Box 1, Folder 11)
  [From original finding aid]: (8 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Zionism: Forerunners of Modern Zionism (Box 1, Folder 12 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (12 typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- Zionism: Forerunners of Modern Zionism (Box 1, Folder 12 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (notebook handwritten containing 10 lectures on the subject)
- Zionism: Monsky The Zionist (Box 1, Folder 13 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (4 typewritten pages, no bibliography, attached newsclipping)
- Zionism: When the U.S. Wavered in Palestine (Box 1, Folder 13 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (4 legal-size typewritten pages, no bibliography)
- The History of Socialism (Box 1, Folder 14 item 1)
  [From original finding aid]: (11 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish, no bibliography)
- Jewish History (Box 1, Folder 14 item 2)
  [From original finding aid]: (1 handwritten pages in cursive Yiddish, no bibliography)
- Three press releases from the Independent Jewish Press Service, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  [From original finding aid]: Eugene Meyer-Secretary of the World Treasury [1946], [Isador Lubin] The Man of Passionate Statistics [1945], Henry Monsky--Jewry Loses An Able Leader [1947]